Finding Aid for Manchester Area Historical Society records, 1837-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Manchester Area Historical Society records 1837-1955 1870-1952
Manchester Area Historical Society.
9535 Cb 2
Collected records, mainly school records, for selected Washtenaw County Townships, notably Manchester, Sharon, Freedom, and Bridgewater; also one volume assessment roll for Freedom Township.
3 linear feet 32 volumes and 45 folders
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from the Manchester Area Historical Society (donor no. 7170 ), February 1995.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
Historical Society serving the city of Manchester in southwestern Washtenaw County, Michigan.
This record group, received from the Manchester Area Historical Society, consists mainly of collected school records for selected Washtenaw County townships in the period between 1837 and 1955. The record group has been arranged by the name of township: Manchester, Sharon, Freedom, and Bridgewater. This record group is approximately three linear feet in size (ca. 32 volumes, 45 folders, and 2 oversize volumes). The school records document financial transactions, as well as school board meeting minutes, student rolls, teacher contracts, and annual reports. Within each of the township series there are subseries for the numbered school districts within each township. The folders in the subseries are arranged alphabetically.
Subjects:
Manchester Area Historical Society.; Bridgewater (Mich.: Township); Freedom (Mich.: Township); Manchester (Mich.: Township); School records.; Schools--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Schools--Records and correspondence.; Sharon (Washtenaw County, Mich.)
- Manchester Township School Records
  The Manchester Township School records series (1870-1953; 11 volumes, 15 folders, and 1 oversize volume) includes records for districts number 2, 4, 5, 6 and 9. A significant portion of district 2 records relate to the establishment of schools, first in 1933 as part of the Civil Works Project and then in 1949 with the building of the Nellie Ackson School.
  - District no. 2
    - Annual Statistical Report 1929-1941
      - 1929-1941 (Box 1)
      - 1942-1952 (Box 1)
    - Civil Works Project 1935-1935 (Box 1)
    - Financial 1926-1955
      - 1926-1933 (Box 1)
      - 1948-1955
    - Minutes 1922-1953
      - 1922-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1947-1953 (Box 1)
    - Nellie Ackson Building
      - General 1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Financial 1949, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - School Development Project 1933 (Box 1)
    - Student Records 1870-1896 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879
      - 1879-1901 (Volume 1)
      - 1883 (Box 1)
      - 1893-1895 (Box 1)
      - 1894-1896 (Box 1)
  - District no. 4
    - Financial 1934-1953 (Box 2)
    - Financial and Minutes 1949-1953 (Box 2)
  - District no. 5
    - Financial and Minutes 1948-1953 (Box 2)
  - District no. 6
    - Financial and Minutes 1948-1953 (Box 2)
  - District no. 9
    - Financial 1944-1952 (Box 2)
  - Various Districts
    - Annual Statistical Reports 1953 (Box 2)
    - Rural District Annexation 1953 (Box 2)
    - School Board Bank Account 1935-1939 (Box 2)
- Sharon Township School Records
  The Sharon Township series (1838-1953; 9 volumes and 10 folders) documents districts number 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 7.
  - District no. 1
    - Electrical Service 1930 (Box 2)
    - Financial 1950-1953
      - 1950 (Box 2)
      - 1951-1953 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1839-1952
      - 1839-1906 (Box 2)
      - 1909-1952 (Box 2)
  - District no. 2
    - Financial 1932-1953
      - 1932-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1945-1953 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1838-1928
      - 1838-1882 (Box 2)
      - 1882-1928 (Box 2)
  - District no. 3
    - Financial and Minutes 1938-1952 (Box 2)
  - District no. 4
    - Financial and Minutes 1949-1953 (Box 2)
    - New Building 1891 (Box 2)
    - Teacher Contracts 1882, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Teacher Term Reports 1874-1884 (Box 2)
  - District no. 5
    - Financial and Minutes 1890-1902 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1860-1880 (Box 2)
    - Student Records 1887-1894 (Box 2)
  - District no. 7
    - Financial 1953 (Box 2)
  - Various Districts
    - Annual Reports 1864-1953 (Box 2)
    - Rural District Annexation 1953 (Box 2)
- Freedom Township
  The Freedom Township series (1845-1953; 9 volumes, 11 folders, and 1 oversize volume) documents districts 1, 3. 6, 7, and 8. In this series, there is also an Assessment Roll for 1876. This volume is the only non-school record in the record group.
  - School Records
    - District no. 1
      - Annual Statistical Report 1927-1952 (Box 2)
      - Financial and Minutes 1910-1952
        - 1910-1931 (Box 2)
        - 1946-1952 (Box 2)
      - Student Records 1884-1909
        - 1884-1892 (Box 2)
        - 1903-1909 (Box 2)
      - Teacher Records 1925-1927 (Box 2)
    - District no. 3
      - Annual Statistical Report 1940-1952 (Box 3)
      - Financial 1950-1952 (Box 3)
      - Financial and Minutes 1866-1951 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1845-1877 (Box 3)
      - Teacher Contracts 1889-1895 (Box 3)
    - District no. 4
      - Student Records 1915-1920 (Box 3)
    - District no. 5
      - Financial 1944-1952 (Box 3)
    - District no. 6
      - Financial and Minutes 1876-1952
        - 1876-1940 (Box 3)
        - 1945-1952 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1837-1875 (Box 3)
    - District no. 7
      - Financial and Minutes 1944-1951 (Box 3)
    - District no. 8
      - Financial and Minutes 1944-1952 (Box 3)
      - Various Districts (Box 3)
    - Annual Statistical Report 1949-1959
      - Oath of Office 1948-1954 (Box 3)
      - School Treasurer Bonds 1945-1951 (Box 3)
  - Assessment Roll 1876 (Volume 2)
- Bridgewater Township School Records
  The Bridgewater Township series (1908-1953; 2 volumes and 5 folders) documents districts 2, 8, and 9.
  - District no. 2
    - Financial 1917-1953 (Box 3)
    - Financial and Minutes 1937-1947 (Box 3)
  - District no. 8
    - Financial 1952-1953 (Box 3)
    - Financial and Minutes 1908-1951 (Box 3)
  - District no. 9
    - Financial and Minutes 1949-1953 (Box 3)
  - Various Districts
    - Annual Statistical Report 1953 (Box 3)
    - Rural District Annexation 1953 (Box 3)
- Townships School Records (Summary Information)
  This series includes general information about the four townships combined.
  - Rural School Inventories undated (Box 3)
  - Rural District Annexation Correspondence 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw County Maps 1952 (Box 3)